Guide to the H. Bruce Franklin Collection SC0152
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
H. Bruce Franklin collection
1969-1980
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Franklin, H. Bruce (Howard Bruce)
SC0152
5.5 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
This collection includes newspapers clippings, Stanford news releases, leaflets and pamphlets relating to Franklin's tenure and dismissal hearings, the full text of the Advisory Board's recommendations, and transcripts of hearing proceedings. Also included are a copy of a senior research project by James Wascher of Northwestern University, 1978; photocopy of a letter from Wallace Stegner, 1972; and the Board of Trustees resolution reaffirming Franklin's dismissal, 1980.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The materials were received by the Stanford University Archives via administrative transfer from Ray Bachetti, Vice-Provost, in 1976. Additional materials were collected by archives staff during the course of the Franklin hearings.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
H. Bruce Franklin had been a member of the English Department faculty since he received his Ph.D. from Stanford in 1961. A highly regarded scholar of Melville, he received tenure in 1965. In his early career at Stanford, Franklin was not publicly involved with politics. He dates the beginning of his political commitment from 1966, when he taught at the Stanford-in-France campus. There he became acquainted with several Vietnamese students, and with them, founded a politically oriented free university in Paris. The controversy concerning Franklin's tenure began in 1971, when he allegedly participated in the heckling of a speech by Henry Cabot Lodge on January 11. The speech was cancelled, and President Lyman sent Franklin a letter of reprimand for his part in the disruptions. Franklin continued to participate in campus demonstrations, however and on March 22 of 1971 was charged by President Lyman for contributing to or inciting disruptions on four occasions: the Lodge disruptions on January 11; a White Plaza antiwar rally on February 10; the occupation of the Computation Center; and a nighttime rally on February 10 which led to subsequent acts of violence on the campus. He was tried before a faculty advisory board of seven full professors. The hearings lasted from September 28, 1971 to January 4, 1972, when the board recommended 5 to 2 that Franklin be fired. The board of Trustees finalized the dismissal on January 20, 1972.
Description of the Collection
The collection includes newspapers clippings, Stanford news releases, leaflets and pamphlets relating to Franklin's tenure and dismissal hearings, the full text of the Advisory Board's recommendations, and transcripts of hearing proceedings. Also included are a copy of a senior research project by James Wascher of Northwestern University, 1978; photocopy of a letter from Wallace Stegner, 1972; and the Board of Trustees resolution reaffirming Franklin's dismissal, 1980.
Academic freedom; Pamphlets; Transcripts; Student movements -- California -- Stanford.; Franklin, H. Bruce (Howard Bruce); Franklin, H. Bruce (Howard Bruce); Stegner, Wallace, 1909-1993; Lyman, Richard W.; Wascher, James D.
- Original accession
  - Stanford University News Service press releases, 1969 Mar 5-1976 Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Press releases covering Franklin's participation in political affairs before his disruption case, during the Advisory Board legal processes, and activities since his Stanford dismissal.
  - Legal documents, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Two Amicus Curiae briefs filed before the Advisory Board in October 1971, and the document relating the decision of the Advisory Board, Jan. 5, 1972.
  - Clippings
    - Clippings related to the Franklin case, 1969 Mar 23-1971 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Clippings related to the Franklin case, 1971 Feb 13-17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Clippings related to the Franklin case, 1971 Mar 1-Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Clippings related to the Franklin case, 1971 Sep 25-Oct 25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Clippings related to the Franklin case, 1971 Oct 26-1972 Jan 5 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Clippings related to the Franklin case, 1972 Jan 6-20 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Clippings related to the Franklin case, 1972 Jan 21-Mar 9 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Clippings related to the Franklin case, 1972 Mar 10-1976 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1971 Jan 18-Mar 12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Photocopies of correspondence related to Advisory Board hearings; major correspondence is between H. Bruce Franklin and Richard Lyman.
  - Ephemera (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Venceramos "press releases"; miscellaneous leaflets and pamphlets related to various aspects of the controversy.
  - Transcripts
    - Lodge incident, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Sep 28: Opening statements, Mercado, Elliot, Overbaugh, Painter, Beckwith. Sep 29: Matthews, Sven, Jacobs, Hanley, Heck.
    - White Plaza and Computation Center, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Sep 30: Ray, Brunot, Painter, Mercado. Oct 1: Painter, Mercado, Williams, Glenn, Press, Heck.
    - Computation Center, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Oct 2: Montgomery, Marron. Oct 4: Wiggins, Begle, Moses, Waterman.
    - Old Union, 1971
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        Oct 5: Dr. Torrin, Beyers. Oct. 6: Beyers, Brimelow, Bennett, Almas
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        Oct 7: Rosa, White, Glenn, Gray. Oct 8: Barr; three tapes played. Administration completes their case.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        Oct 11-12: Motion to dismiss and response.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
        Oct 13: Newcomer, Barkley, Siegel. Oct 14: Weiss, Knecht, Silvestri.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
        Oct 15: Sandra Kahn, F. Silvestri, Paul Wolf, Mark Savin, Sandra Peterson, Jane Franklin.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
        Oct 18: G. Campbell, Alford, Fricke, Don Lee, D. Laney, HBF. Oct 19: HBF (on Lodge).
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        Oct 20: HBF (redirect). Oct 21: Braunstein, Gocking. Oct 22: Herzenberg.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 2)
        Oct 23: Hardegree, Eklof, Homsy, Downey. Oct 25: C. Stein, Montgomery, Barkan, J. Yudken, Van Dyke
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
        Oct 26: Barkan, Sutter, Michael, Nelson, Crouse, McNellis, Little, Kahn.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 1)
        Oct 27: Kahn, Cornell, Youdelman, Knutson, Loeb. Oct 28: Litterman, Appel, Harrison, Switzer, Hunkeler, Lonsdale.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Oct 29: Cerney, Pace, Doering, HBF (on WP and CU). Oct 30: HBF, Rubenstein, Faulkner (2), O'Fallon, Jessup, Karish, Rabine.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        Nov 1: Kimball, Walker, Bennion, Cummings, Karp, Henner, HBF. Nov 2: HBF, Youdelman, Borock, rebuttal; W. F. Miller, Broholm, Siegel.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 1)
        Nov 3: Owen Blank, HBF.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 2)
        Nov. 4: Closing Arguments: Admin.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
        Nov. 5: Closing Arguments: HBF.
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 4)
        HBF Final Supplementary Written Brief
      - Transcript: Old Union, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 5)
        University's Supplemental Brief
  - Wascher, James D. Academic Freedom and the Campus Revolution: the dismissal of H. Bruce Franklin, 1978; 167 leaves (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Typescript copy. Senior research project, Northwestern School of Law, May 16, 1978.
  - Stanford University Board of Trustees, resolution reaffirming Franklin's dismissal (photocopy), 1980 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Stegner, Wallace, letter to Jay Miller, ACLU of Northern California (photocopy from Mrs. Wallace Stegner), 1972 Feb 21 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-1989-133
  - Franklin, H. Bruce, From the Movement Toward Revolution, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Faculty defendants' supplemental memorandum of points and authorities in opposition to plantiff's motion for summary judgment and in support of defendants' support of defendants' motion for summary judgment (Box 1)
  - Memorandum of points and authorities in opposition to plantiff's motion for summary judgment and in support of defendants' motion for summary judgment (Box 1)
  - Advisory board correspondence: Franklin hearing, 1971 Apr-Sep (Box 1)
  - "Academic Freedom at Stanford: Lessons of the Franklin Case" Science, 1972 Mar 17 (Box 1)
  - Packer, Herbert L., "Academic Freedom and the Franklin Case" Commentary, 1972 Apr (Box 1)
  - Hearings Before the Committee on Internal Security House of Representatives, Ninety-Third Congress, Second Session: Terrorism, Part 1, 1974 Feb-Mar (Box 1)
  - America's Maoists: The Revolutionary Union; The Vehnceremos Organization. Report by the Committee on Internal Security, House of Representatives, Ninety-Second Congress, Second Session, 1972 Jun 22 (Box 1)
  - Franklin hearing, 1967-1976 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2017-125
  - News releases and clippings re activism and Franklin's dismissal., circa 1971 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH-2017-333
  - "In the Matter of Professor H. Bruce Franklin" (ACLU Brief) (Box 1)
  - Advisory Board Decision, 1972 Jan 5 (Box 1)